&intro=When Plains Indians first met Indians from other tribes, Spanish explorers, or Anglo settlers, they could not speak their languages. So they created signs with their hands that stood for important words. In the following activity you will test your language skills by trying to match certain signs with the words they represent.
&ins=<strong>INSTRUCTIONS:</strong> Click on the word in the middle that you think best represents the sign language picture on the left. As you correctly identify the sign for each word, the Spanish translation of that word will appear beside it.  Keep watching the box on the right to see a surprise picture of a real sign language expert!