&title_main=How to Say the Same Word in 7 Different Languages
&maintext=Say you're traveling across Texas in the 1800's and you're getting mighty hungry. You come across several groups of people, but none of them speak your language. What word could you use to communicate that you wanted something to <font color='#FF0000'>eat</font>?
&english=English - eat
&spanish=Spanish - comer
&comanche=Comanche - tehcaró
&karankawa=Karankawa - akna'mas
&coahuiltecan=Coahuilteco - hām

&subtext=It would be difficult for anyone to learn all these different words. No wonder the Plains Indians made up a sign for the word "eat" that everyone could understand! And the sign is the same one used today by hearing-impaired persons using American Sign Language(ASL).
&exptext=The sign for "EAT" in both Plains Indian Sign Language and American Sign Language