In this rear compartment, the archeologists made a remarkable discovery. Amid coils of rope and brass wire, ammunition, and other items, they found two wooden boxes filled with the items La Salle had hoped to use for bartering with native peoples in the New World. According to Principal Investigator James Bruseth, these small “trader” chests, brimming with diminutive objects of metal and glass, are unique in North American archeology.  Packed inside the first box were hundreds of brass Jesuit rings tied together with string along with stacks of wooden combs, cans of small round mirrors, and dozens of knives.  The second box contained some 600,000 glass beads—white, black, and cobalt blue—still strung on their original thread and wrapped around a piece of rope to bind them in place. This treasure represented a substantial expenditure paid for personally by La Salle and his men, as the French king did not provide funds for trade goods.  In addition to the two boxes, archeologists also uncovered 22 wooden barrels in the aft hold, along with rope and coils of brass wire, the “duct tape” of the time. 
After excavating and removing the jumbled cargo, archeologists found another layer of remains at the bottom of the aft hold: bricks from the cooking galley, empty wine bottles, animal bones, eating utensils, and game pieces. Crewmembers had gathered in this small, makeshift cooking galley to have meals, play games, and escape the cold, likely while the ship was anchored for months in Matagorda Bay. 