&title_main=Create Your Own Sign Language!
&maintext=There are many ways to tell a story, and spoken language is only one of them. The Plains Indians used hand signs to speak to each other, and scholars recorded these signs as pictures.
Using paper and a pencil, create your own set of original sign-pictures to tell a story or joke. Think of 5-10 words you want to use, then draw simple pictures to illustrate them.
After your pictures are complete, use them to tell your story to your class. Or better yet, let a classmate see if they can "read" your story from your pictures!
&break

&title_help= Helpful Hints for Creating Your Sign-Pictures
&subtext=It woudl be difficult for anyone to learn all these different words. No wonder the Plains Indians made up a sign for the word eat that everyone could understand! And the sign is the same one used today by hearing impaired persons using American Sign Language(ASL).
&exptext1=Use arrows to show how the hands should move. For example, the Plains Indian sign for "up"
&exptext2=Use dotted lines to show the hands moving back and forth or up and down. For example the Plains Indian sign for "deer"
&hints=Hints for telling your sign language story:
&hint1=Use only your hands to sign with.
&hint2=A sign made with only one hand is usually made with the right hand.