&title_main=History of Plains Indian Sign Language 
&maintext=No one really knows exactly where or when Plains Indian sign language began to develop. We do know, however, that when the Spanish explorer, Francisco Vásquez de Coronado visited Texas in 1541-1542, he used sign language to communicate with the Indians he met there. Some researchers believe that sign language began even earlier, in south Texas, where hundreds of Indian groups had to find a way to communicate with one another as they moved from place to place in search of food. 
When the various groups of Indians began riding horses and traveling greater distances, they also began widespread trading with other Indian groups who spoke different languages. In order to communicate with each other, these Indians began developing a language of hand signs that could be used all over the Great Plains. 
It is said that a good sign talker could conduct a conversation in sign language nearly three times as fast as he could speak. The Kiowa Indians had a reputation as some of the best and fastest signers. 
Although at one time as many as 3,500 different signs were being used, by the 1880s Plains Sign Language was no longer commonly used on the Great Plains. Plains Indians had been forced to attend English-speaking schools where they lost not only their sign language, but most of their spoken languages as well. Today, formal signing is a symbol of Indian identity and can be seen at ceremonials and Pow-Wows all over the country. 
Many deaf Native Americans, as well as thousands of other hearing impaired persons, speak another kind of sign language as well. American Sign Language, or ASL, the language of the American deaf community, is taught in many schools and universities and is the fourth most commonly used language in the U.S.! 
&exptext1=Map of Plains Indian Tribes
&exptext2=Map of South Texas Plains Indian Tribes